You may have heard
the expression
“knowledge is power.”
Well, today we’re going
to give you more power
to control your
diet and lifestyle
by giving you the facts.
Welcome to the
Nutrition Facts Podcast.
I’m your host,
Dr. Michael Greger.
Today we have the first
in an eight-part series
on how industries impact
dietary and health guidelines.
And we start with Big Sugar.
In 2019, a series of reviews
was published in the
Annals of Internal Medicine
that concluded the same thing
that past reviews have concluded:
adherence to dietary patterns
lower in red or processed meat
intake may result in decreased risk
for premature death, cardiometabolic
disease and mortality,
meaning the risk of getting
and dying of diseases
like heart disease and type 2
diabetes, as well as the risk
of getting cancer
and dying from cancer,
therefore, they concluded in their
Dietary Guideline Recommendations,
“continue [your] current
red meat consumption,”
“continue [your] processed
meat consumption.”
Wait, what?! Yeah, premature
death, cancer, heart disease,
diabetes, but keep eating
your burgers and bacon.
To understand what just happened,
we have to go back to 2015.
The Dietary Guidelines
had just had the audacity
to recommend people
reduce their sugar intake.
Imagine you work
for the sugar industry.
The evidence is overwhelmingly
against you; what do you do?
Well, what did the
tobacco industry do?
One method involved the
tobacco industry’s funding of
and involvement in seemingly
unbiased scientific groups
to manipulate the scientific
debate concerning tobacco and health.
Groups like the ILSI, the
International Life Sciences Institute,
which has enjoyed a long
and serious collaboration
with the tobacco industry,
that same industry group, shapes
food policy around the world.
The International Life
Sciences Institute (ILSI),
technically a nonprofit with
an innocuous sounding name
“has been quietly
infiltrating government health
and nutrition bodies
around the world.”
It was created by a top
Coca‑Cola executive, and
“almost entirely funded by
Goliaths of the agribusiness,
food, and pharmaceutical industries.”
“After decades largely
operating under the radar,
the Institute is coming
under increasing scrutiny
by health advocates in the
United States and abroad who say
it's little more than a front
group advancing the interests
of the 400 corporate members,”
among them Coke and Pepsi.
So, when the 2015 dietary
guidelines advised eating less sugar,
the soda-funded International
Life Sciences Institute
sponsored a review
concluding that the guidelines
on sugar were simply not trustworthy.
Who did they pick for this
hatchet job? Bradley Johnston.
And here it is, published in
the Annals of Internal Medicine.
The Scientiﬁc Basis of Guideline
Recommendations on Sugar Intake,
and concluded there basically wasn’t one.
“Guidelines on dietary sugar do
not meet criteria for trustworthy
recommendations as they are
based on low-quality evidence.”
“This comes right out of
the tobacco industry’s playbook:
cast doubt on the science,”
said Professor Marion Nestle,
“This is a classic (shameful) example of
how industry funding biases opinion."
Yes, the paper was
paid for by the likes of
Coca-Cola, Hershey, Red Bull,
and the makers of Oreos.
But the authors swore
they wrote the protocol
and conducted the study independently.
It turns out that was a lie,
forcing the journal to publish
a corrected version after the
Associated Press obtained emails
showing the industry front
group “requested revisions.”
It also came out that a co-author
conveniently forgot to mention
a $25 grand grant she got
directly from Coca-Cola.
You know it’s bad when
candy bar companies criticize
an industry-funded paper on sugar.
The maker of Snickers, Skittles,
and M&M’s broke ranks with
other food companies and
denounced the industry-funded paper.
They themselves were a member
of the ILSI, but come on,
telling people to ignore
guidelines to cut down on sugar?
That’s just making us all look bad.
If you look at the relationship
between funding source
and the conclusions in nutrition-
related scientific articles,
there’s like seven or eight times
the odds that the conclusion
will skew favorably compared to
studies with no industry funding.
For interventional studies, the
proportion of studies paid for
by industry that reached unfavorable
conclusions about their own
products was a big fat 0 percent,
which should not surprise anyone.
So, what can journals do
to counteract the tactics
that industry often uses to
advocate for the safety
of unsafe products, or
question the integrity of science
that calls their products into question?
To combat the tobacco industry's
inﬂuence over scientiﬁc discourse,
leading journal editors have
refused to be passive conduits
for articles funded by
the tobacco industry.
They just won’t accept tobacco
industry-funded studies period.
Accordingly, high-quality
journals could refrain
from publishing studies on
health effects of added sugars
funded by soda and cookie
companies. But they’re not.
This was published in the
Annals of Internal Medicine.
And so, four years later, with the
next batch of dietary guidelines
on the way, and the
last scientific report
of the guidelines committee
encouraging people to eat diets
not just lower in sugar
but lower in meat as well.
Big Beef decided to follow in
the footsteps of Big Butterfinger.
Same journal, same guy,
same scientist-for-hire,
Bradley Johnston, as lead
author, and the rest is history.
We’ll dig into exactly
how he pulled it off next.
In 2016, a Washington-based lobby
group published a scientific review
which concluded that evidence
in favor of guidelines
recommending limits on added
dietary sugar was “low quality”
and did not “meet criteria
for trustworthy recommendations.”
This was a group funded by multinational
food and agrochemical companies
from Coca-Cola to Monsanto to
the captains of corn syrup,
accused of “hijacking the scientific
process in a disingenuous way
to sow doubt and
jeopardize public health.”
But exactly how did
they get away with it?
Here’s their paper,
questioning the scientiﬁc basis
of guideline recommendations
on sugar intake.
Using the “GRADE” approach, they
concluded that the overall quality
of evidence to support such
recommendations was low to very low.
GRADE stands for the Grading
of Recommendations Assessment,
Development and Evaluation initiative,
which was developed to make
clinical guidelines more evidence-
based and thank heavens for that.
Clinical guidelines, like
which drug to give to whom,
used to be developed by
something like the GOBSAT method,
(just some Good Old Boys
Sitting Around a Table).
Under GRADE, high-quality
evidence appears
to be derived exclusively
from randomized trials.
This is not surprising given that
the GRADE process was designed
for drugs, and, of course, you
want your drugs put to the test.
Like remember the Premarin
story, where for a decade,
organizations recommended
that clinicians encourage
postmenopausal women to use
hormone replacement therapy,
because women who were taking it
appeared to have fewer heart attacks.
But when put to the test,
randomized controlled trials
instead showed the opposite.
So, we definitely want drugs put
through randomized double-blind,
placebo-controlled trials,
where people are randomized
to take the drug or unknowingly
take a placebo instead,
and no one knows
who’s in which group
until the code is broken at
the end, and you see how well
the two groups did
compared to each other.
Everyone agrees that
randomized controlled trials
are enormously valuable in
many areas of medical research,
such as the testing of drugs,
but wait a second,
how do you do that with diet?
There’s no such thing
as a placebo diet.
How can you randomize
people to different diets
but somehow hide from them
which diet they’re following?
People tend to notice what
they put in their own mouths.
And RCTs (randomized controlled
trials) are so expensive
they typically last for
only weeks or months,
but it takes most cancers
decades to develop;
so, it’s nearly impossible
to see if different diets
prevent or cause
cancer that way.
To see if smoking causes cancer,
you can follow large cohorts
of smokers and nonsmokers out
for decades to see who gets cancer
and who doesn’t, but it’s not
like you can randomize people
to smoke or not smoke for decades.
When studying lifestyle interventions,
you often just can’t do
randomized controlled trials,
and even if you could,
it might not be ethical.
Take crib death, for example,
sudden infant death syndrome.
A pivotal study studying the
habits of infants who died
discovered that sleeping on
their stomachs was a risk factor;
so, we started educating
parents “face up to wake up,”
and the SIDS rates dropped.
What more do we need?
Would it even be ethical to randomize
thousands of babies to sleep
on their backs or fronts and
count up the deaths at this point?
You can get sufficient evidence
to make lifestyle recommendations
that save lives without
randomized controlled trials.
Critical questions, like
“What dietary pattern produces
the best health outcomes
over a lifetime?”
simply can’t be answered with
randomized controlled trials.
You can’t randomize people
to different lifetime diets
and expect them to stick to them;
so, we need to compile an amalgamation
of evidence from other study designs.
The lack of evidence from
randomized controlled trials
has become a common
argumentation strategy
for criticizing nutrition
recommendations.
Similar claims were made by
the tobacco industry in its attempt
to discredit evidence
on the harms of tobacco.
Case in point: the so-called
“sound science” campaign
carried out by Philip Morris.
This is all straight out of
the tobacco industry playbook.
Philip Morris used public relations
firms and lawyers to develop
a “sound science” program that
involved recruiting other industries
and issues to obscure the
tobacco industry’s role.
They tried to enshrine
“good epidemiological practices”
that would make it impossible to
conclude that secondhand smoke—
and thus other environmental
toxins—caused diseases.
“Public health professionals
need to be aware that
the ’sound science’ movement
is not an indigenous effort
from within the profession
to improve the quality
of scientific discourse, but
rather reflects sophisticated
public relations campaigns
controlled by industry executives
and lawyers whose aim is to
manipulate the standards of
scientific proof to serve the
corporate interests of their clients,”
and not just tobacco clients
but they hope to expand
to the food, plastics,
and chemical industries.
Philip Morris went beyond just
“creating doubt” and “controversy”
about the scientific evidence,
to attempting to change
the scientific standards of proof.
But randomized
controlled trials aren’t
the only source
of good evidence.
As Sir Bradford Hill himself
said, who pioneered the randomized
controlled trial: “Any belief
that the controlled trial
is the only way to
go would mean
not just that the pendulum
had swung too far
but that it had come
right off (the) hook.”
We would love it if you could
share with us your stories
about reinventing your health
through evidence-based nutrition.
Go to nutritionfacts.org/testimonials.
We may share it on our social
media to help inspire others.
To see any graphs, charts, graphics,
images, or studies mentioned here,
please go to the Nutrition Facts
Podcast landing page.
There you’ll find all the
detailed information you need –
plus, links to all of the sources
we cite for each of these topics.
For a timely text on the
pathogens that cause pandemics,
order the e-book,
audiobook, or hard copy
of my last book,
“How to Survive a Pandemic”.
For recipes, check out
my second-to-last book,
my “How Not to Diet Cookbook”.
It’s beautifully designed
with more than 100 recipes
for delicious and
nutritious meals.
And all the proceeds
I receive from the sales
of all my books goes to charity.
NutritionFacts.org is a nonprofit,
science-based public service,
where you can sign up
for free daily updates
on the latest in nutrition research
via bite-sized videos and articles.
Everything on the
website is free.
There’s no ads, no
corporate sponsorship.
It’s strictly non-commercial.
I’m not selling anything.
I just put it up as a public service,
as a labor of love,
as a tribute to my grandmother,
whose own life was saved
with evidence-based nutrition.